Exercise 4.
Reflection.
The Hall of Mirrors. The Right Hand Path.
Find a place where you will be comfortable.
Relax your body, your mind, and your spirit, and we will begin
your fourth journey into the Shadow Realm.
You close your eyes and empty your mind.
You imagine that the gold and silver chain is clasped around
your neck and that the key is hanging over your heart.
You imagine yourself grasping the key and holding it tightly in
your hand.
You feel the power of the key's energy growing stronger as you
hold it. As the power of the key's energy increases, it is
pulling you away from the earthly plane.
You feel yourself drifting slowly downward, away from the
mundane world.
With every beat of your heart, you drift ever closer to the
borders of the shadow realm.
You can now see the twilight of the Shadow Realm growing more
intense as you approach your domain.
The twilight's magical luminescence begins to surround you and
you feel the power of the Shadow Realm growing stronger as you
pass through the protective energies of its boundaries.
You see See the massive walls of stone that encircle the Shadow
Realm, and the two slowly spinning circles of power below you.
You slow your descent, and you hover directly over the two
crystalline circles of energy and magic.
The Shadow Realm looks exactly the same as it did the last
time you saw it, but somehow it feels very different.
Wild energies seem to be flowing freely throughout every corner
of the Shadow Realm.
Your presence here is somehow supercharging these energies, and
you can feel an intense and powerful magical force emanating
from the center of your domain.
As you look down towards the center of the Shadow Realm, you
see that the heart of this intense energy seems to be focused
around the frame of the mirror. You also see that once again,
you have visitors. The gruff -voiced old gentleman and the kind
-hearted elderly woman are sitting on the white marble floor
next to the soul sword.
They seem to be playing some kind of a board game.
Intrigued, you float down and pass through the crystalline
circles to get a closer look. look.
You now see that they are playing a game of chess.
There are only two pieces left on the board, a white king
and a black king.
The elderly gentleman looks up at you and sighs.
Neither one of us can win this game, he says, sounding almost
exasperated, but but she makes me keep playing it with her
anyway.
My dear sir, the elderly woman exclaims, you are very well aware
of the reasons why we can't stop playing this game. She moves
the white king to an open square on the chessboard.
She's right, he says, as he moves the black king randomly to
another square.
He looks up and catches your eye.
Life is not a game that can be either won or lost,
he says to you. Only played.
The elderly woman smiles at the old man, takes his arm to
brace herself, and gingerly rises to her feet.
You see that she is wearing an old white apron that is
very badly stained, its edges tattered and worn.
You find yourself feeling sorry for her for having to wear such
an old rag of an apron.
As if she had read your mind, the old woman looks at
you and says, Don't feel sorry for me, dear. These are the
stains of life. We all have them, you know. I just wear
this old thing to remind me. Besides, not all of these stains
are bad ones. Yes, quite a few of them make me sad
when I remember, but just as many are pleasant to recall.
An amused smile crosses your face as you realize the truth and
wisdom within the old woman's words.
She now motions for you to come closer. You go to her
side, and she takes you by the arm.
Be a dear and walk me to the mirror, she begs. I
need to check my hair and makeup.
Her grasp on your arm is warm and comforting.
You reach over and wrap your hand over hers.
Her skin is as thin as tissue paper.
It feels soft and pleasing in the palm of your hand.
You slowly walk with her to the mirror.
As you approach the mirror, arm in arm with the old woman,
Woman, you are mindful of where she is stepping.
Just as I thought, the old woman exclaims, I'm quite the mess.
You glance up at the looking glass, and your breath stutters in
your chest.
The elderly woman's reflection reveals her to be the most
beautiful, most imperious woman you have ever seen.
A blazing crescent burns upon her forehead. head.
I am known by 10 ,000 names and I have worn 10
,000 faces.
It is now the goddess who speaks to you.
Each and every person sees the facet of me that they need
to see. There are many facets to you also and you too
bear the stains of life, she says as she takes the key
hanging over your heart into her hand.
The key starts glowing with powerful energies, and tiny beams of
light begin to shine and dance across the shaft of the key.
The elderly gentleman now walks over to you and stands at your
other side.
He begins to speak.
You must embrace every aspect of yourself, he says, both the
good and the bad. You must accept the stains of your life,
be they light or dark.
He reaches past you and takes the hand of the goddess, so
that they are both holding the key, and as he does, the
rays of light surrounding it grow brighter and more intense.
When you look up and see the old man's reflection in the
mirror, you are not surprised.
He is the god.
He is powerful, yet inviting.
Wisdom and light shine in his eyes. A symbol of the sun
burns upon his chest.
The god and goddess slowly open their hands.
The key has been transformed into a large gemstone with
thousands of facets cut into its surface. Each facet shines with
its own unique ray of light.
Open your hands, my dear, the goddess says. You cup your hands
and hold them open in front of you the god and goddess
place the gemstone in your palms and fold your fingers around
the sparkling jewel the gemstone feels very warm in your hands
you can feel the energies within the stone begin to move through
your fingers your hands and arms are beginning to tingle with a
sensation that you have never felt before suddenly you notice
that the tips of your fingers are are beginning to crystallize,
to sparkle with facets, just like the gemstone you hold in your
hands.
You look to the god and the goddess, as if asking them
what is happening to you.
It's nothing to worry about, the goddess assures you. You are
merely taking on a different form for now.
The voice of the god also sounds. She is right, he says.
You are changing, but this is nothing for you to fear. But
you should probably get going before the transformation is
complete.
The god and the goddess take you by the arms and lead
you into the living waters of the looking glass of the mirror.
They release their hold on your arms and you float away from
them and enter the portal of the mirror.
The waters of the mirror flow around you like thick warm honey,
soothing you as you pass into them.
You feel as if you are floating inside the womb of the
goddess herself. The glow emanating from the gemstone in your
hands begins to grow brighter, and the stone rises up until it
is hovering inches above the palm of your hands.
The gemstone slowly begins to spin in a prism of color and
light. The shafts of light bouncing off the thousands of facets
sparkle and glitter, becoming more intense with every revolution
of the gemstone. stone.
You also see shafts of light are bouncing off the crystal facets
that your fingertips have become.
You can now feel that you are somehow absorbing the thick warm
waters of the looking glass into your body through your crystal
fingertips.
As the living waters enter your fingers and begin to flow inside
you, you see that your hand and arms are now also becoming
crystalline. You raise your arms and hands before you in wonder.
Even though you are transforming into a human gemstone, you are
still able to move your body with the fluidity of the living
water itself.
You feel the crystallizing waters flow up into your shoulders
and through your chest. They cascade down through your hips and
legs, transforming every inch of your body.
The waters now well up and wash into your throat and over
your your face. They flow over your temples and forehead, and at
last, the living water stream through your eyes like reversed
tears.
You are suddenly seen through the kaleidoscopes of the faceted
crystal lenses of your new eyes.
For the first time in your life, you know what it might
be like to see through the eyes of deity.
With your crystal in vision, You see a comet as it races
past a dying star in the deepest recesses of space.
You see a child as it is being born into the world,
another child as it dies in its mother's arms.
You see a gray -bearded old man tending a fire deep in
the wilderness.
You see an ocean of people as they walk the streets of
a large city.
You feel the loneliness and desperation of an old woman as she
stares out of her window, watching life pass her by on the
streets below you see through the eyes of a young man as
he gazes down upon the world from the top of a mountain
you feel the unity of life on earth and you feel humble
to be a part of the oneness of the world the images
and emotions of a thousand lives and a thousand deaths flash
before your crystalline eyes pass through your crystalline mind.
The images and emotions combine into visions that are coming to
you faster than you can grasp them. The emotions you feel wash
over you like a mighty waterfall.
To try to slow the momentum of feelings and visions, you focus
your eyes and your mind on the gemstone, which is still slowly
spinning and floating a few inches above your hands.
But the visions keep coming, faster and and faster, pouring into
your crystalline eyes, filling your crystalline mind.
You see that the rays of light beaming from the slowly spinning
gemstone are generating the visions.
You see that the visions are also being reflected onto the
countless facets that cover your crystalline body.
You know that you must quickly figure out some way to gain
control over the visions before you are completely overwhelmed
by them.
You intensify your focus and concentration on the slowly
spinning crystal.
The crystal stops spinning and you look deeply into a single
facet on the surface of the crystal floating just above your
hands.
The vision in this facet seems to freeze and hold in time
but something else happens as well. The countless other visions
also seem to be slowing down, but you can feel them building
into an unstoppable deluge behind the single frozen vision on
the surface of the crystal.
You know that it could be dangerous to hold back these visions
for long.
You know that you have only a few seconds of clear thought
before you have to release the visions. You can feel that the
energies within the facet are somehow sending the vision into to
your body and your mind through the beams of light emanating
from the gemstone.
The energies within a facet feel very familiar to you and you
quickly recognize them as being the same energies that make up
the sun side of the looking glass of the mirror.
You know that the looking glass of the sun side of the
mirror is made up of flow energy and that it is capable
of either sending or deflecting energy. energy.
You trace the beam of light emanating from the frozen facet on
the gemstone to a single crystalline facet on your arm.
As you look deeply into the facet on your arm, you see
that the vision is frozen within this facet as well, but the
energies within the facet on your arm feel very different from
the energies of the gemstone. stone.
You recognize these energies as being the same as those that
make up the moon side of the looking glass of the mirror.
You know that the moon side of the looking glass is made
up of counter flow energy and that it is capable of drawing
energies into it.
You now know that it is the counter flow energies within the
facets on your crystalline body that are drawing the visions
inside of you.
Now you remember that you have learned how to reverse the flows
of energy around you by switching your sending and receiving
hands. This gives you an idea.
You slowly uncup your hands and the crystal floats away into the
air above you.
You cross your crystalline arms.
You concentrate on the counter flow energy within the single
frozen facet on your arm.
using your will and the magical skills that you have learned you
concentrate on reversing the counter flow of energy within the
single crystal facet on your arm
The reverse flow slowly begins to work and you can see and
feel that the vision in the facet is being deflected. It is
moving away from you.
You now see that the deflected vision is still caught up in
the beam of light emanating from the gemstone. The energies
within the facet on the gemstone and the reversed energies
within the facet on your arm are now trying to send the
vision in opposite directions.
This causes the gemstone to resume spinning.
You can now feel the countless other visions swelling up within
the facets on your crystalline body and mind.
The dam is about to break. You ignore them for now as
you keep the deflective energy stream of the reverse counter
flow concentrated on the single vision that is caught up in the
gemstone's beam of light. light.
You can see and feel that the powerful controlling force of the
flow energy is now combining with the deflective force of the
reverse counter flow of energy.
You release your hold on the reverse counter flow of energy and
the counter flow returns turns to normal.
It is now working in perfect harmony with the flow energy.
You can now use the power of the combined flows to guide
the vision to anywhere you desire.
You quickly use the force of the combined energy streams to move
the vision away from from the beams of light being generated by
the spinning gemstone.
You look at the single vision being held at bay by the
combined streams of flow and counterflow.
You are arrested by the wonder of what you are seeing.
The single vision is no longer frozen in time, it is playing
out as normal within the looking glass of a small mirror that
has somehow been created within the stream of flow and counter
flow energy.
Not only is the vision carrying on as it should, but you
can now look upon the vision without it being overwhelming to
you. You have gained control over the vision. you can now use
and manipulate the vision in any way you see fit.
You can feel that the countless other visions are quickly
building again behind the dam of your crystalline mind, so you
concentrate on tapping the sum of the power within the stream of
flow and counter flow energy around you.
The stream quickly builds into a powerful flood and washes over
the countless facets that cover your crystalline body.
As the controlling power of the combined energy streams flow
over each crystal facet of your your body. Each vision is caught
up in the flood of flow and counterflow, and one by one
they begin moving away from your mind and body.
You now see a very strange sight. There are now hundreds of
small looking glasses floating within the powerful combined
streams of flow and counterflow energy all around you.
Each Each of these small looking glasses is reflecting a
different vision.
The number of looking glass visions quickly grows. There are now
countless thousands of reflected visions surrounding you.
Thousands more are being washed away from your crystalline body
by the energy tides of the flow and counter flow.
One by one they are being added to the ever growing ocean
of looking glass visions.
There seems to be no organization as to where the looking glass
visions are appearing. How are you ever going to keep track of
all of them?
As if in silent response to your concern, the gemstone slowly
floats up and into the stream of flow and counter flow energy.
It hovers in the center of the ever -increasing ocean of
visions.
You are astonished to see that the beams of light emanating from
the spinning gemstone are somehow locking onto each of the
looking glass visions.
the beams are connecting them together and locking them into
place next to each other the looking glass visions are being
organized into a monstrously huge sphere that resembles the
faceted gemstone itself
the few remaining visions are now flowing away from you and are
being drawn up and locked into place by the light beams of
the gemstone stone.
You gaze upon the gigantic faceted sphere made up of looking
glass visions.
As before, you are held in wonder by the power and beauty
you behold.
You focus on a single vision on the sphere, and the vision
within the looking glass is projected directly in front of you
like a hologram.
Fascinated by the possibilities, you take a few moments to learn
what you can see and feel within the vision that is being
projected in front of you.
You now know that you can use the looking glass facets of
the vision sphere to see, feel, and experience anything,
anywhere within the universe at any time you desire.
Something suddenly calls to you in your mind.
It is time for you to return to the shadow realm.
The living waters of the looking glass portal begin to drain
away from your body.
As the living waters leave your body and form a pool beside
you, the crystal facets of your body begin transforming back to
flesh and blood. flood.
The last few droplets of water drain away from your fingertips.
The looking glass portal has been restored.
As you begin to move toward the shimmering pool of the Looking
Glass portal, something suddenly distracts you. The gigantic
sphere of the countless visions is growing smaller.
The spinning gemstone floats toward you, and as it comes closer,
you see that it is returning to its former shape. It is
turning back into the necklace and the key.
The silver and gold necklace slides over your head, and now the
key is once again hanging over your heart.
The vision sphere has now grown so small that you can barely
make it out in the distance.
There is a sudden flash of bright light, and the vision sphere
disappears altogether, almost like a UFO vanishing into the
night sky.
A second smaller flash of light near your chest draws your
attention back to the key resting over your heart.
You see that the vision sphere has shrunk down to the size
of a small stone.
It has embedded itself into the shaft of the key.
As you take the key into the palm of your hand, you
are instantly transported through the looking glass portal and
back into the shadow realm.
The first thing you see in the shadow realm is the old
woman. She is sitting on a large wooden trunk next to the
moon pool. She appears to be sewing something together with
silver thread that is rising from the pool. pool.
You also see that the griffin is not only awake, but that
it is resting next to the sun pool as it plays a
game of chess with the elderly gentleman.
Looking more closely at the board, you can see that the elderly
gentleman is losing quite badly to the griffin.
I never win at this stupid game, the old man grumbles, as
he lays his king on its side and concedes the game.
He looks the griffon sourly in the eye and says, good boy,
now lie down and go back to sleep.
The griffon chuckles, jumps back up on top of the mirror frame,
closes its eyes, and it slowly turns to stone.
You now see that the old woman has hidden whatever it was
she was sewing inside the chest.
She closes the lid, turns the latch, then turns and looks you
in the eye.
Never mind that for now, she says. It will be safe in
there until you need it. The elderly gentleman has also risen to
his feet, and he and the old woman give each other a
kind and loving glance.
The old woman walks behind the moon pool and stands there
quietly The elderly gentleman walks behind the sun pool and does
the same
He now speaks one more time
Never forget how far you have come on your journey, he says
Never forget what you have learned Use your knowledge and skills
wisely and humbly Know that I will always be there for you
when you need me
He closes his eyes and his skin begins to turn gray He
is transformed into a statue of a wise and powerful god
The old woman also speaks one more time Guard well the powerful
key that hangs over your heart, my dear The vision sphere
embedded into its shaft is there for you to use whenever you
need it Use it to learn the ways of all peoples and
of all magics
Pass on your teachings. Share what you have learned with all who
would know the ways of power.
She, too, closes her eyes and is transformed into a statue of
a wise and powerful goddess.
A gentle wind begins to blow in the shadow realm. Its breeze
touches your forehead, and you are calmed by its presence.
You are at peace with yourself.
You sit down before the great mirror of promise and magic.
Within the living waters of the looking glass you can see only
your own reflection and this comforts you.
You have accomplished a great deal this day. It is now time
for you to leave the shadow realm.
You grasp the key in the palm of your hand.
As the key grows warm, you begin your ascent toward the waking
world.
You slowly drift up through the crystal circles and towards the
boundaries of the shadow realm.
You are very near the edge now, very close to the earthly
plane.
The key grows warmer in the palm of your hand.
You cross over the boundaries of the shadow realm. You open your
eyes and your mind to the waking world.
Thank you.